Guide to the Southwest Pennsylvania NASW Pioneers Oral History Project, 1998-2006 AIS.2004.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Southwest Pennsylvania NASW Pioneers Oral History Project
1998-2006
ULS Archives & Special Collections
National Association of Social Workers. Pennsylvania Chapter
AIS.2004.10
0.21 Linear Feet (1 box)
The Pioneers Program was officially established by the National Association of Social Workers (NASW) in 1994 in order to recognize social workers who have made significant contributions to the profession. In 1999, the Southwest Pennsylvania chapter of the NASW Pioneers began an oral history project in order to document the experiences of retired social workers in the region. The information gathered reveals the interesting variety of work performed by social workers over the last seventy years, including their involvement in providing direct services to people, community organizing, and influencing social policy development. Summaries of the interviews were then created and collectively published. This collection consists of copies of the summaries as well as ten audiocassettes containing recordings of some of the interviews.
History
In 1994, The National Association of Social Workers (NASW) officially established the Pioneer Program in order to recognize social workers who have made significant contributions to the profession. Two years later, the Southwest Pennsylvania chapter of the NASW Pioneers formed with the intent of documenting the history of social work in this region as well as providing a sense of connection between generations of those in the field. To this end, Barbara K. Shore, Ph.D., formed a committee in 1999 to record the oral histories of retired social workers.
The committee chose to focus on the development of social work in a number of different contexts, including health and family agencies, schools, services to the poor and aging, Jewish agencies, unions and community organizations and group work agencies serving Pittsburgh's Hill district. Names of the potential participants were obtained from the Pennsylvania chapter of the NASW. Those interviewed are professionals who graduated with social work degrees prior to 1950. The Southwest Pennsylvania Pioneers created a form in conjunction with the University of Pittsburgh's School of Social Work to be used during the interview. In order to guarantee the resulting information could be used for research and publication, the interviewees were asked to sign permission forms. For accuracy's sake, a number of interviews were recorded to tape. The interviewers then wrote summaries of the conversations and sent them to the interviewees for their review and approval.
Scope and Content Notes
The thirty-eight oral history interviews reveal the interesting variety of work performed by social workers over the last seventy years, including their involvement in providing direct services to people, community organizing, and influencing social policy development. The range of activities of social workers has broadened, but the emphasis has not shifted from understanding the needs of individuals in complex situations or crisis. The relationship between human development and societal forces continues as a theme throughout social work's history and is brought to light through the interviews.
The names of the interviewers are included in the case file. The existence of an audiocassette containing a recording of the interview is noted when applicable.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Southwest Pennsylvania NASW Pioneers on May 21, 2005.
Existence and Location of Copies
There are ten audiocassettes containing interviews with several participants of the project.
Previous Citation
Southwest Pennsylvania NASW Pioneers Oral History Project, 1998-2006, AIS.2004.10, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
The published transcripts have been cataloged and are available through the University Library System as HV98.P4 S68 2002.
Social action; Social workers; Transcripts; Audiocassettes; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Social service -- Pennsylvania; Social service -- History -- 20th century; Societies; National Association of Social Workers. Pennsylvania Chapter; O'Brien, James E.; Page, Mary H.; Plutchok, George; Richardson, Ruth G.; Risko, George J.; Scheafnocker, W. E.; Scherb, Edith; Shore, Barbara K.; Sillins, Catherine Kinley Melaney St. Clair; Snyder, Stanley; Steytler, Anne; Taylor, Dorothy; Thomas, Eleanora M.; University of Pittsburgh. Graduate School of Social Work; Wynne, Margaret M.; Bakich, Patricia J.; Bilder, Shirley Meyers; Bolden, Nancy L. Travis; Brieland, Donald; Brown, Sydney Taylor; Burgess, Alma; De Silva, E. Gregory; Devereaux, Lois Sullivan; Dolan, Canice; Dunmore, Charlotte J.; Forsström, Vera; Goldberg, Marcella Cohen; Greenberg, Lois; Hamilton, Catherine; Hawkins, Alexander A.; Hawkins, Mabel T.; Hepner, Betty Shore; Hiltner, Robert; Judkis, Edna; Kaplan, Naomi; Lederman-Stolzer, Shirley; Lovette, Thelma W.; Malley, Mary; McDonald, Inez Womack
- Patricia J. Bakich, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Shirley Meyers Bilder, December 10, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Nancy L. Travis Bolden, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Donald Brieland, April 5, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Sydney Taylor Brown, February 2, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Alma Burgess, August 2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- E. Gregory De Silva, October 28, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Lois Sullivan Devereaux, September 20, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Canice Dolan, August 10, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Charlotte Dunmore, August 7, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Vera Scholl Forsstrom, March 3, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Marcella Cohen Goldberg, September 20, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Lois Greenberg, May 10, 2002; (audiocassette available) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Catherine Hamilton, July 8, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Alexander A. Hawkins, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Mabel T. Hawkins, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Betty Shore Hepner, November 17, 1999; (audiocassette available) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Robert Hiltner, July 6, 1999; (audiocassettes available) (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Edna Judkis, December 9, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Naomi Kaplan, June 14, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Shirley Lederman-Stolzer, January, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Thelma W. Lovette, August 29, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Mary Malley, June 23, 1999; (audiocassette available) (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Inez Womack McDonald, July 24, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- James E. O'Brien, September 27, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Mary H. Page, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- George Plutchok, July 9, 2001; (audiocassette available) (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Ruth G. Richardson, February, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- George J. Risko, September 10, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- William E. Scheafnocker, April 30, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Edith Scherb, March 23, 2000; (audiocassette available) (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Barbara K. Shore, December 23, 1999; (audiocassette available) (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Catherine Kinley Melaney St. Clair Sillins, January 21, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Stanley Snyder, February 3, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Anne Steytler, December 7, 1998; (audiocassette available) (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Dorothy Taylor, February 19, 1999; (audiocassette available) (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Eleanora M. Thomas, August 3, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Margaret M. Wynne, January 29, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 38)